You often describe going
against the grain as
giving up on your own
terms.  Will
correct practice
always go against
your preferences, or
might there
come a time when you
truly prefer to
prefer to
go against the grain, once
you understand what that
means?
Yes, I think
it will almost certainly go
against your
preferences at first.  Um, because
theoretically it doesn't have to
be that
way.  But I suppose
such people would have
become arahants long ago, while the
arahants long ago, while the
Dhamma was much more
alive.  Today we
have people who,
you know, didn't try
hard enough
when Buddha was around.
So, for example,
the need
to follow
rules, if
you look at, say,
food, lying,
entertainment, and of course,
sexuality, this is
already quite at
odds with the life of an
ordinary, decent
person today.    I mean
, you know, I don't
mean someone
very immoral,
just a regular
person.  You know,
a little lie, this or
that—it's no big
deal.  You may not
be a liar or a
cheat, but
entertainment, food,
sexuality—what is
considered normal today, what
normal today, what
is considered a
baseline for 99.9% of people—
will be at odds with
that, and therefore, in one way or
another, it will be
unpleasant.  But that's exactly how it is
, of course.  Once
you start
practicing, if you
start understanding
things correctly, if
wisdom really
develops, and things
are really understood,
not just
intellectually accepted and so on
accepted and so on
, the motivation for
practice, the purpose of
practice, obviously becomes even
obviously becomes even
stronger, even
clearer.  So
then even
having to
put up with those very
moments when you have to say "
when you have to say "
no" to desires,
unhealthy tendencies, etc., won't be even
tendencies, etc., won't be even
a little unpleasant, because
you know exactly where
it leads.  You
know for sure that the result of
this will be much
better than if you
just gave in to
it.  Therefore, the
more a person
practices, the
clearer things become
, the easier the
whole experience of this
practice becomes.  And that's why
this can't happen
by chance.  This is possible
only through your
own efforts to go
against the current until you and
your mind begin to
prefer renunciation.  You will begin to
renunciation.  You will begin to
prefer
solitude to
company, renunciation
to desire,
peace to
excitement.  This is why
the Buddha encouraged
monks to develop
the enjoyment of
solitude.  And he said to
them: monks,
practice renunciation
, in essence, develop the
joy of renunciation,
so that your mind
ceases to seek
sensual pleasures.
Cultivate the pain of
renunciation to
replace the pains of
family life or a
life of sensual
pleasures.  So you are
actually perfecting your
perfecting your
pleasures and pains
by replacing sensual ones with those
associated with
renunciation.  And then there
comes a moment when
recognizing the mind
of desire and abandoning
it becomes a
pleasant touch.
Because again, if
I give you a poisonous
drink and you don't know it's
poisonous, or you
don't believe me, and you're
so obsessed with
the taste, addicted to
it, because it's the
most amazing taste
you can
imagine.  You won't
stop drinking it.  But then you
drinking it.  But then you
find out it's
poison.  You start to
notice symptoms.  You
start to notice
the difference and see
changes in yourself when you don't
drink it.  So, you
confirm to yourself
that there
is poison in the drink I gave you.    Is
there anything I could have
said or done
to get you to drink it
when the danger became
obvious?  It's like, "Oh
no, no chance."
Or look, he's
twice as nice
as he was before.  It doesn't
matter.    The
real threat to
your life becomes
apparent: if you
interact with it, you are
putting yourself in
danger.  And it
will take a lot of
effort to undo
this impact, if you are
lucky and
have enough time
to fix it.  This is
how you recognize it,
and then you will happily
say “no” to taste,
sight, sound, smell,
touch, and so on.  And
you will be very happy about
this, because
you realize that you are
avoiding trouble.  And this
relief is
real.